<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anno regni Caroli regis Angliæ, Scotiæ, Franciæ, &amp; Hiberniæ, decimo septimo at the Parliament begun at Westminster the third day of November, anno Dom. 1640 ... : an act for the speedie and effectuall reducing of the rebells in His Majesties kingdom of Ireland to their due obedience to His Majestie and the Crown of England.</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37588</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E1127</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41133</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19638116</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19638116</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109249</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37588)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109249)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1685:55)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anno regni Caroli regis Angliæ, Scotiæ, Franciæ, &amp; Hiberniæ, decimo septimo at the Parliament begun at Westminster the third day of November, anno Dom. 1640 ... : an act for the speedie and effectuall reducing of the rebells in His Majesties kingdom of Ireland to their due obedience to His Majestie and the Crown of England.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Barker ... and by the assignes of John Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Other title information taken from caption title on p. [3].</note>
                  <note>At head of caption title: Anno XVII, Caroli regis.</note>
                  <note>"Cum privilegio."</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained with print show-through and loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109249:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>decorative frame</figDesc>
               <p>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</p>
            </figure>
            <p>ANNO REGNI CAROLI REGIS ANGLIae, SCOTIae, FRANCIae, &amp; HIBERNIae, DECIMO SEPTIMO.</p>
            <p>At the Parliament begun at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the third day of November, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1640.</p>
            <p>In the 16. yeer of the Reign of our moſt gracious Soveraign Lord, CHARLES, by the grace of God, of England, Scotland, France, and Ireland King, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by ROBERT BARKER, Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſtie: And by the Aſſignes of JOHN BILL.</p>
            <p>1641.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum Privilegio.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:109249:2"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               <p>C R</p>
               <p>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PEN</p>
               <p>DIEV ET MON DROIT</p>
            </figure>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="act">
            <pb facs="tcp:109249:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> ANNO XVII. Caroli Regis.</head>
            <head>¶ An Act for the ſpeedie and effectuall reducing of the Rebells in His Majeſties Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> to their due obedience to His Majeſtie and the Crown of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, taking into their ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſiderations, as well the neceſſity of a ſpeedie reducing of the Rebells of <hi>Ireland</hi> to their due obedience, as alſo the great ſums of money that the Commons of this Realm have of late paid for the publike and neceſſary affairs of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, whereof the Lords and Commons are very ſenſible, and deſirous to imbrace all good and honourable wayes, tending to His Majeſties great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and profit, the ſetling of that Realm, and the eaſe of His Majeſties Subjects of <hi>England;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:109249:3"/>
And whereas divers worthy and well-affected perſons, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that many Millions of Acres of the Rebells Lands of that Kingdom, which go under the name of profitable Lands, will be confiſcate, and to be diſpoſed of; And that in caſe two Millions and a half of thoſe Acres to be equally taken out of the four Provinces of that Kingdom, may be allotted for the ſatisfaction of ſuch perſons as ſhall disburſe any ſums of money for the reducing of the Rebells there, would effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally accompliſh the ſame, have made theſe Propoſitions en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That two Millions and an half of thoſe Acres may be aſſigned, allotted, and divided amongſt them after this proportion, <hi>(viz.)</hi> For each Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of two hundred pounds, one thouſand Acres in <hi>Ulſter:</hi> For three hundred pounds, one thouſand Acres in <hi>Conaght:</hi> For four hundred and fifty pounds, one thouſand Acres in <hi>Munſter:</hi> For ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds, one thouſand Acres in <hi>Leinſter.</hi> All ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Engliſh meaſure, and conſiſting of Meadow, Arable, and profitable Paſture, the Bogs, Woods, and barren Mountains being caſt in over and above theſe two Millions and a half of Acres, to be holden in free and common Soccage of the King, as of His Caſtle of <hi>Dublin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That out of theſe two Millions and a half of Acres, a conſtant yeerly rent ſhall be reſerved to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> after this proportion, <hi>(viz.)</hi> out of each Acre thereof in <hi>Ulſter</hi> one penie; Out of each Acre in <hi>Conaght,</hi> three half pence; Out of each Acre in <hi>Munſter,</hi> two pence farthing; And out of each Acre in <hi>Leinſter,</hi> three pence; whereby His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Revenue out of thoſe Lands will be much improved, beſides the advantages that he will have by the coming to his hands of all other the Lands
<pb facs="tcp:109249:3"/>
of the Robells, and their perſonall Eſtates, without any charge unto His Majeſtie.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That for the erecting of Mannors, ſetling of Waſts, and Commons, maintaining of preaching Miniſters, Creating of Corporations, and Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating of the ſeverall plantations, one, or more Commiſſions be hereafter graunted by authoritie of Parliament.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That Moneys for this great occaſion may be the more ſpeedily advanced, All the Vndertakers in the Citie of <hi>London,</hi> and within twentie miles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant thereof, ſhall underwrite their ſeverall ſums be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the twentieth day of <hi>March,</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred fourtie one, and all within ſixtie miles of <hi>London,</hi> before the firſt day of Aprill, one thouſand ſix hundred fourtie two, and the reſt of the Kingdom before the firſt day of May, one thouſand ſix hundred fourtie two.</p>
            <p n="5">5 That the ſeverall ſums to be underwritten, ſhall be paid in at four paiments, <hi>(viz.)</hi> One fourth part within ten dayes after ſuch underwriting, and the other three parts at three Moneths, and three Moneths, all to be paid into the Chamber of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 That for the better ſecuring of the ſaid ſeverall ſums accordingly, every one that doth ſo Vnderwrite ſhall at the time of his Subſcription pay down the twentieth part of the totall ſum that ſhall be by him then underwritten. And in caſe that the reſidue of his firſt fourth part be not paid in to ſuch perſon, or perſons as ſhall be appointed to receive the ſame,
<pb facs="tcp:109249:4"/>
within the ten dayes before limited, then ſuch party ſhall not onely forfeit the twentieth part of the ſum totall formerly depoſited, but ſo much more of his firſt fourth payment to be added thereunto, as ſhall make up the one Moyetie of the ſaid fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t payment. And if the ſame perſon ſhall fail in any other of the three paiments, he ſhall then forfeit his entire firſt fourth part, and all the benefit of his Subſcription, which forfeiture ſhall accrue to the common benefit of the reſt of the underwriters.</p>
            <p>And whereas aſwell our Soveraign Lord the King, as the Lords and Commons have approved of the ſaid Propoſitions, and aſſented that the ſaid Propoſitions, and all other things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily conducing thereunto, ſhall be ratifyed and confirmed by authoritie of Parliament;</p>
            <p>Be it therefore Enacted by Our Soveraign Lord the King, with the aſſent of the Lords and Commons in this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament aſſembled, and by authoritie of the ſame, That all and every of the ſaid Propoſitions, and every clauſe therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, are, and ſhall be according to the tenour and purport thereof hereby ratified, eſtabliſhed, and confirmed, with ſuch explanations, alterations, and additions, as in this Act are expreſt.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted, That all and every perſon, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which upon the three and twentieth day of October, in the yeer one thouſand ſix hundred fourtie one, or at any time after ſhall be in Rebellion, or levie war againſt the Kings Majeſtie, within His Realm of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or ſhall willingly aid, aſſiſt, or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance any perſon or perſons in Rebellion againſt the Kings Majeſtie, ſhall loſe and forfeit unto the Kings Majeſtie, His Heires and Succeſſors, all ſuch right, title, intereſt, uſe and poſſeſſion, which they, or any of them, or any other perſon or perſons in truſt for them, or any of them, on the ſaid three and twentieth day of October, or at any time after ſhall have, of, in, or unto any Honours, Caſtles, Mannors, Meſſuages, Lands, Tenements, Rents, Annuities, Reverſions, Remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Vſes, Poſſeſſions, Offices, Rights, Conditions, or any other Hereditaments, of what name, nature, or qualitie ſoever
<pb facs="tcp:109249:4"/>
they be, and that all ſuch right, title, intereſt, uſe and poſſeſſion, which they or any of them, or any other perſon or perſons in truſt for them, or any of them, on the ſaid three and twentieth day of October, or at any time after ſhall have, or of right ought to have, of, in, or to the ſame Honours, Caſtles, Mannors, Meſſuages, Lands, Tenements, Rents, Annuities, Reverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Remainders, Vſes, Poſſeſſions, Offices, Rights, Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or any other Hereditaments, ſhall by the authoritie afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, be deemed veſted, adjudged, and taken to be in the actuall and reall poſſeſſion of Our Soveraign Lord the King, His Heirs and Succeſſors, without any Office or Inquiſition there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hereafter to be found.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That two Millions and a half of Acres of Meadow, Arable Land, and profitable Paſture, which are, or ſhall be forfeited by the ſaid Rebels, or otherwiſe by vertue of this Act; With Woods, Boggs, Loughes, and barren Mountains caſt in over and above, and with all the Buildings and Edifices thereupon, are, and ſhall be by vertue of this Act, for the ſatisfaction of ſuch perſon, and perſons as ſhall underwrite any ſum, or ſums of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and pay the ſame according to the true intent and meaning of this preſent Act, the ſame to be allotted, and apportioned to each Vnderwriter according to the proportion of the ſums to be underwritten, and paid in, and to be holden by ſuch Rent, and Tenure as in the ſaid recited Propoſitions are expreſſed.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, That <hi>John Warner, John Towſe,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Andrews</hi> Aldermen, and <hi>Lawrence Halſted</hi> Eſquire, are, and ſhall be hereby appointed, and authoriſed to give their daily attendance at the ſaid Chamber of <hi>London,</hi> to receive all ſuch Subſcriptions, and ſums of Money, and to give receipts for the ſame under their hands, as ſhall be there tendred and paid ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Act, which ſaid perſons ſo appointed to receive the ſaid ſums of Money, ſhall enter the names of the Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writers, together with the ſum, and time of Subſcription, into one, or more Books to be kept for that purpoſe, and ſhall from time to time iſſue out the ſaid ſums of Money, in ſuch manner as both Houſes of Parliament ſhall by Order direct.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, That the Sheriffs of each Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>England,</hi> and Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> ſhall receive all ſuch Subſcriptions, and ſums of Money, as ſhall be by vertue of this Act tendred to them in their reſpective Counties, and ſhall appoint dayes, and places for that purpoſe, and ſhal give receipts
<pb facs="tcp:109249:5"/>
for the ſums ſo received under their hands, and return the ſums ſubſcribed and received, together with the names of the Vnderwriters, and the times of their Subſcriptions, to the Chamber of <hi>London,</hi> to the hands of the ſaid <hi>John Warner, John Towſe, Thomas Andrewes,</hi> and <hi>Lawrence Halſted,</hi> or to any two of them, with all convenient ſpeed, to be by them entred into Books to be kept for that purpoſe: And they, the ſaid <hi>John War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, John Towſe, Thomas Andrewes,</hi> and <hi>Lawrence Halſted,</hi> or any two of them, are hereby likewiſe authoriſed, and required to give acquittances or receipts for all ſums received of the ſaid Sheriffs: And that the ſaid <hi>John Warner, John Towſe, Thomas Andrewes,</hi> and <hi>Lawrence Halſted,</hi> and the ſaid Sheriffs, their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and miniſters, their heirs and executors, ſhall accompt for all ſums of Money by them received according to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Act, to ſuch perſons as both Houſes of Parliament ſhall direct.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That it ſhall and may be lawfull, to, and for the ſaid <hi>John Warner, John Towſe, Thomas Andrewes,</hi> and <hi>Lawrence Halſted,</hi> and the ſaid Sheriffs reſpectively, to deduct, and retain to their own uſe, one peny out of every pound, of all ſuch ſums of Money as they ſhall receive according to this Act, towards their charges and pains in attending and receiving the ſaid Subſcriptions and ſums of Money, and in iſſuing out, and returning up the ſame.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted, That when the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of this Realm of <hi>England,</hi> ſhall in Parliament by Order Declare, that the ſaid Rebels are ſubdued, and that this preſent Rebellion in the ſaid Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> is appeaſed, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that forthwith after ſuch Declaration made, and ſent to the Lord Chancellor, or Lord Keeper of the great Seal of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> for the time being, the ſaid Lord Chancellor, or Lord Keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is hereby authoriſed, and required to iſſue forth Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons into all the ſaid four Provinces of that Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> for the ſurveying, and ſetting forth of the ſaid two Millions and half of Acres, which Commiſſion ſhall be to ſuch effect, and directed to ſuch perſons as the ſaid Lords and Commons in Parliament ſhall appoint; Which ſaid Commiſſioners ſhall have power by this Act, to ſurvey all the Lands of the ſaid Rebels, and all the Lands forfeited by vertue of this Act, and to aſſertain, and meaſure forth of the ſame ſix hundred and five and twenty thouſand Acres, in every of the ſaid four Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb facs="tcp:109249:5"/>
of Meadow, Arable and profitable Paſture, with Woods, Bogs, Loughes, and barren Mountains caſt in over and above, with the Houſes and Edifices thereupon; and after the ſame meaſured and ſet forth, ſhall indifferently divide the ſame by Lot among the ſeverall Vnderwriters, and among the heirs of ſuch Vnderwriters as ſhall die before the diviſion, and the aſſignee, and aſſignees of ſuch of the Vnderwriters as ſhal aſſigne their ſhares, or any part thereof before the ſaid Diviſion, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Proportions mentioned in the ſaid recited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, and according to the reſpective ſums paid in, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and according to the purport of this preſent Act; which Diviſion ſhall be made in ſuch manner as the ſaid Lords and Commons in Parliament ſhall by Order direct; in which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion no manner of favour or advantage ſhall be given or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to any perſon whatſoever, but all to be done and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined equally, and by Lot, and each Vnderwriters Land to be laid together, or ſo neer together as conveniently may be. And in caſe ſix hundred twenty five thouſand Acres of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels profitable Lands, and of the profitable Lands forfeited by vertue of this Act, ſhall not be found in each Province, then ſo much of the ſaid ſix hundred twenty five thouſand Acres, as ſhall be wanting in any one Province, ſhall be made up in value out of the ſaid Rebels Lands; and for want thereof, out of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Lands forfeited by this Act in the other Provinces, at the diſcretion of the ſaid Commiſſioners, reſpect being had to the value of the Lands in each Province, according to the ſaid propoſitions; which ſaid Commiſſioners ſhall return the ſaid allotments, and all their proceedings therein fairly ingroſt in parchment into His Majeſties Court of Chancery of this Kingdom, there to remain of Record, and into His Majeſties Court of Chancery of the ſaid Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to remain there likewiſe of Record:</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted, That immediately after eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Vnderwriter, Heir or Aſſignee of any Vnderwriter, ſhall have drawne his reſpective Lot, containing the Meadow, Arable, and profitable Paſture, with all the Woods, Bogs, Loughes, and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren Mountains over and above, together with the houſes and edifices thereupon, which ſhall be appointed for his ſhare, ſuch Vnderwriter, Heir, and Aſſignee ſhalbe, and ſo ſhalbe adjudged to be, by vertue of this Act, in the actuall poſſeſſion, and ſeiſin of all the ſaid lands, with all things thereunto belonging, mentioned in his ſaid Lot, and that he ſhall &amp; may forthwith after his Lot
<pb facs="tcp:109249:6"/>
ſo drawn as aforeſaid, enter upon, have and enjoy to him and his heires, all and ſingular the Meadow, Arable, profitable Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, Woods, Bogs, Loughes, Waters, Fiſhings, and barren Mountains, together with the Houſes and Edifices thereupon, and in his ſaid Lot contained, with all Eaſements and Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities thereunto belonging.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the authority aforeſaid, That all and every perſon and perſons, which within three moneths af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the allotment ſo to be made as aforeſaid, ſhall have one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Acres, or more of the ſaid two millions &amp; half of Acres, lying together in the Province of <hi>Leinſter,</hi> or two thouſand Acres, or more lying together in the Province of <hi>Conaght,</hi> or one thouſand five hundred Acres or more lying together in the Province of <hi>Munſter,</hi> or three thouſand Acres or more, lying together in the Province of <hi>Ulſter,</hi> ſhall have power by vertue of this Act, for every ſuch thouſand, two thouſand, fifteen hundred, and three thouſand Acres, to create a Mannor within the limits of the ſaid lands reſpectively, and to reſerve tenures to hold of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his heirs, as of his ſaid Mannor or Mannors, at his will, and pleaſure: And that every ſuch perſon ſhall have a Court Leete, and Court Baron, and ſhall have full power to hold a Court Leete, and Court Baron within the Precincts of every ſuch Mannor, and to enjoy all ſuch Royalties, Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſes, Fines and Amerciaments, Suites, Services, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities, as to view, of Franke pledge, or Court Baron, is uſuall and belonging. And alſo within each reſpective Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, to have and enjoy as aforeſaid, all Deodands, Felons goods, and goods of Felons, of themſelves, together with all Wayfes and Strayes.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the authority aforeſaid, That no part of the monie which ſhall be paid in according to this Act, ſhall be imploied to any other purpoſe then the reducing of the ſaid Rebels, untill the ſaid Rebels ſhall be declared to be ſubdued by the ſaid Lords and Commons, as aforeſaid. And that the ſaid monies ſhall be imploied for the ſpeedie and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall ſubduing of the ſaid Rebels by ſending over into the ſaid Realme of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and diſpoſing there ſuch forces of Foot, and Horſe, Monies, Ammunition, Victuall, and all other things neceſſary to a warre, in ſuch manner as the ſaid Lords, and Commons in Parliament ſhall from time to time direct, and the overplus of the ſaid money, if any ſhall be, to be diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as the ſaid Lords and Commons ſhall likewiſe direct.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:109249:6"/>
And be it likewiſe enacted by the authority aforeſaid, That Plantations ſhall be regulated, Corporations created, Churches erected, and Preaching Miniſters maintained within the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits and Precincts of the Lands ſo to be divided, in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as by Commiſſioners to be nominated and directed by the ſaid Lords and Commons in Parliament ſhall be ordered and provided.</p>
            <p>And it is further enacted, That the Lord Chancellour or Lord Keeper of the Great Seal of <hi>England</hi> for the time being, ſhall upon direction to him given by the ſaid Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in Parliament, iſſue out one or more Commiſſions for this purpoſe, directed to ſuch perſons, and in ſuch manner, as the ſaid Lords and Commons in Parliament ſhall order and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point.</p>
            <p>And for the further encouraging and ſecuring of all ſuch perſons as ſhall pay any ſum of money towards the perfecting of this great Work, Be it likewiſe enacted by the authority aforeſaid, That all Patents which ſhall be granted of any of the ſaid Rebells goods or Lands, or of any goods or Lands forfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by vertue of this Act, and all Pardons which ſhall be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to any of the ſaid Rebells before attainder, after the three and twentieth of October, one thouſand ſix hundred fourty and one (without the aſſent of the ſaid Lords and Commons in Parliament) ſhall be adjudged void, and of none effect.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the authority aforeſaid, That the Commiſſioners authoriſed by this Act to ſet forth the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writers Lands, as aforeſaid, ſhall fourty dayes before they ſet forth the ſame, or any part thereof, cauſe Proclamations to be made by vertue of this Act, in every Countie of the ſaid King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to this effect, <hi>(viz)</hi> That every perſon which had any right, title, or intereſt the three and twentieth of Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tober one thouſand ſix hundred fourty one, in, or out of any of the ſaid Rebells Lands, or the Lands forfeited by this Act, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing within the Countie where any ſuch Proclamation ſhall be made, ſhall enter his claim to the ſame upon record in His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Court of Chancery in the ſaid Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in twenty dayes after the ſaid Proclamation ſo made in the ſaid Countie.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the authority aforeſaid, That every perſon which after the firſt day of March, one thouſand ſix hundred and fourty, ſhall make, enter into, or take any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact,
<pb facs="tcp:109249:7"/>
Bond, Covenant, Oath, Promiſe, or Agreement, to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, or bring into the ſaid Realm of <hi>Ireland</hi> the authority of the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> in any caſe whatſoever, or to maintain or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the ſame, ſhall by vertue of this Act, forfeit to His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, His Heirs, and Succeſſours, all his Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments entailed or not entailed, Goods and Chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels, which he had or ſhall have in his own name, or any other perſon or perſons had or ſhall have in truſt for him, at the time of the making, entring into, or taking any ſuch Compact, Bond, Covenant, Oath, Promiſe, or Agreement, other then ſuch Lands, Tenements, Hereditaments, Goods and Chattells, as ſhall be <hi>bona fide,</hi> and for valuable conſideration ſold, before the ſaid three and twentieth of October, one thouſand ſix hundred fourty one.</p>
            <p>And further be it enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That if any perſon, ſince the three and twentieth day of October, one thouſand ſix hundred fourty one, be, or hereafter ſhalbe in Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion within the ſaid Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and be dead, or ſhall die before attaindor, or pardon for the ſame; All the Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments, Eſtate, or Eſtates, Goods or Chattells which ſuch perſon had, or ſhall have, or any other perſon had, or ſhall have in truſt, for, or to his uſe, the ſaid three and twentieth of October, or at any time thereafter, ſhall be by vertue of this Act forfeited to His Majeſtie, His Heirs and Succeſſours, and ſhall be adjudged to be in the actuall ſeiſin and poſſeſſion of the King, His Heirs and Succeſſours, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of this Act.</p>
            <p>And further be it enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That all Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments, whereof any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the ſaid Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> was ſeiſed the three and twentieth of October, one thouſand ſix hundred fourty one, or at any time after, ſhall be ſeiſed of any Eſtate, tail, or whereof any other perſon or perſons ſhall be ſeiſed in truſt for him, for any truſt of inheritance, who ſhall be attainted of high treaſon in his life time, or being in actuall Rebellion ſhall die before he be attainted, or pardoned for the ſame, or who ſhall make, enter into, or take any ſuch Compact, Bond, Covenant, Oath, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe or Agreement to ſuch purpoſe as aforeſaid, ſhall by vertue of this Act, be, and adjudged to be in the actuall ſeiſin and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the King. His Heirs and Succeſſours.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That if
<pb facs="tcp:109249:7"/>
any perſon or perſons whatſoever, that at any time hereafter ſhall be attainted for Treaſon, or ſhall die in actuall Rebellion before attaindor, or pardon of the ſame, or hath, or ſhall take, enter into, or make any ſuch Compact, Bond, Covenant, Oath, Promiſe, or Agreement as aforeſaid, ſhall after the firſt day of March, one thouſand ſix hundred and fourty, make, or hath made any Conveyance, or Aſſurance whatſoever, of any Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, Lands, Tenements, or Hereditaments in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> unto, or for his own uſe, or unto, or for the uſe of his wife, or any of his children, or in truſt for himſelf, his wife, or any of his children; That then all the Vſes, Eſtates, and Truſts ſo limited, other then ſuch as are, or ſhall <hi>bona fide</hi> be made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his, her, or their marriage, or made in performance of any Covenant in writing made before marriage, unto, or for the uſe of his wife or children, ſhall be forfeired unto His Majeſtie, His Heirs and Succeſſours, and ſhall be adjudged to be by vertue of this Act, in the actuall poſſeſſion of the King, His Heirs and Succeſſours.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, in regard a great part of the time preſixed in the ſaid Propoſitions for the ſubſcriptions of the ſaid Vnderwriters is already elap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that every one of the Kings Subjects of the Realms of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland,</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> that ſhall underwrite within this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom the ſumme of ten pounds, or more, for the purpoſe afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, before the firſt day of <hi>May</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred fourty two, and before the ſaid Million of Money be underwritten, and ſhall pay in one moiety thereof to the reſpective Receivers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nominated in this Act at the time of ſuch ſubſcription, and ſhall pay in the other moiety reſidue thereof to the ſaid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers within ſix Moneths after ſuch ſubſcription: and every one of the Kings Subjects of the Realms of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> that ſhall underwrite the ſumme of ſix pounds, or more, within the Realm of <hi>Ireland</hi> for the purpoſe aforeſaid (in one or more Books to be kept for that purpoſe by the Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of the Armie there for the time being) who is authorized, and required hereby to keep ſuch Book, or Books, and to enter the names of ſuch Vnderwriters, and the time of ſuch ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, together with the ſummes ſubſcribed, before the firſt day of <hi>July</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred fourty two, and before the ſaid Million of Money ſhall be underwritten, and ſhall at the time of ſuch ſubſcription pay one moietie of ſuch ſumme ſo to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derwritten
<pb facs="tcp:109249:8"/>
to the ſaid Treaſurer for the time being (who is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by likewiſe authoriſed to receive all ſuch ſums of Money, and give Receipts for the ſame under his hand) and ſhall pay to the ſaid Treaſurer the other moietie reſidue within ſix moneths af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch ſubſcription, every perſon ſo underwriting in this Realm, or in the Realm of <hi>Ireland,</hi> as aforeſaid, ſhall have a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable ſhare of the ſaid Rebells Lands, and of other Lands to be forfeited by this Act, according to the ſum to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written and paid in, as aforeſaid, and as if ſuch perſon had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derwritten within the times mentioned in the ſaid Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and had paid in his money accordingly.</p>
            <p>And for the better advancing of a ſpeedie Plantation within that Kingdom, which will ſoon redound to the great increaſe of His Majeſties Cuſtomes and Revenues there, Be it further enacted by the Authoritie aforeſaid, That every perſon which ſhall have any part of the ſaid lands ſo to be divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and allotted, as aforeſaid, ſhall and may export out of this Kingdom, or Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> any Horſes, Mares, Cattell, Sheep, or other goods, for the planting, improving, and ſtock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſaid lands, or any part thereof, at any time during the ſpace of two yeers, to be accounted from ſuch diviſion and allotment to be made (as aforeſaid) without paying any Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, Subſidie, or Impoſt for the ſame. Nevertheleſſe, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſufficient ſecuritie given to the Farmers, or Collectors of His Majeſties Cuſtomes, for the time being, or to any one of them, that the ſaid Horſes, Mares, Cattell, Sheep, and goods ſo to be exported, ſhall be <hi>bona fide</hi> imployed for the planting, impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and ſtocking of the ſaid lands, or of ſome part thereof, and not to be imployed to any other purpoſe. Saving to all and ſingular perſons, bodies Politique, and Corporate, their Heirs and Succeſſors, and the Heirs and Succeſſors of every of them (other then the ſaid Rebels, their Aiders, Abettors, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forters, and Maintainers, and other perſons, whoſe lands are, or ſhall be forfeited by this Act, and every of them, their, and every of their Heirs and Aſſignes, and all and every perſon or perſons clayming, by, from, or under them, or any of them, or to their, or any of their uſe or uſes, or in truſt for them or any of them, ſince the ſaid three and twentieth day of October) all ſuch Right, Title, Intereſt, Poſſeſſion, Reverſion, Remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Offices, Annuities, Rents, and Commons, which they, or any of them had, or ought to have had in, to, or out of any the
<pb facs="tcp:109249:8"/>
ſaid Houſes, Mannors, Caſtles, Lands, Tenements, Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taments, or Premiſſes, forfeited by this Act, or any of them, the three and twentieth day of October, in the yeer of our Lord God, one thouſand ſix hundred fortie one, ſo as every ſuch perſon or perſons, bodies Politique, or Corporate, whoſe right or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt is ſaved by this Act, their Heirs or Succeſſors do make or enter, or cauſe to be entred, his, or their claim to any ſuch right, title or intereſt, in His Majeſties Court of Chancerie in <hi>Ireland,</hi> within twentie dayes after ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation made as aforeſaid.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
